<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.8.5">
  <compounddef id="indexpage" kind="page">
    <compoundname>index</compoundname>
    <title>GROMACS</title>
    <innerpage refid="page_analysisframework">Framework for trajectory analysis</innerpage>
    <innerpage refid="page_onlinehelp">Help formatting</innerpage>
    <innerpage refid="page_usinglibrary">Using GROMACS as a library</innerpage>
    <innerpage refid="page_wrapperbinary">Wrapper binary implementation</innerpage>
    <innerpage refid="page_simd">Single-instruction Multiple-data (SIMD) coding</innerpage>
    <innerpage refid="page_refdata">Using reference data in C++ tests</innerpage>
    <innerpage refid="page_modulegraph">Module dependency graph</innerpage>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>GROMACS is a versatile package to perform molecular dynamics, i.e. simulate the Newtonian equations of motion for systems with hundreds, to millions of particles. See <ulink url="http://www.gromacs.org">www.gromacs.org</ulink> for more information.</para><para>This documentation generated by Doxygen is (mostly) extracted from the source code, and provides documentation for understanding the source code. The documentation can be generated with different levels of details. This documentation has been generated to include all documentation, including internal functions and classes used for internal implementation purposes.</para><para>The main audience for this level of detail are people who want to understand detailed implementation of some area, or try to find some specific function within the library. If you are overwhelmed by the amount of details, the <ulink url="../html-lib/index.xhtml">library API documentation</ulink> skips functions not meant to be used outside a single module.</para><para>Currently, only parts of the code are documented here. The following pages give an overview of some of the topics that are documented:</para><para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ref refid="page_analysisframework" kindref="compound">Framework for trajectory analysis</ref> <linebreak/>
 Provides an overview of the framework that the GROMACS library provides for writing (trajectory) analysis tools.</para></listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="page_onlinehelp" kindref="compound">Help formatting</ref> <linebreak/>
 Provides an overview of the formatting markup available in help texts.</para></listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="page_usinglibrary" kindref="compound">Using GROMACS as a library</ref> <linebreak/>
 Provides general guidance for writing software that uses the GROMACS library.</para></listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="page_wrapperbinary" kindref="compound">Wrapper binary implementation</ref> <linebreak/>
 Provides an overview of how the <computeroutput>gmx</computeroutput> wrapper binary is implemented.</para></listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="page_simd" kindref="compound">Single-instruction Multiple-data (SIMD) coding</ref> <linebreak/>
 Documentation about the new SIMD module that makes it possible to write highly accelerated CPU code that is still portable.</para></listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="page_refdata" kindref="compound">Using reference data in C++ tests</ref> <linebreak/>
 Documentation for writing tests that use reference data generated by the same test.</para></listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="page_modulegraph" kindref="compound">Module dependency graph</ref> <linebreak/>
 Automatically generated module dependency graph.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
</para><para>This list will hopefully expand over time. </para>    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
